{
    "questions": [
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following method of revenue assessment is related to the Vijayanagara Empire?",
            "optionA": "  Chauth ",
            "optionB": "  Ryotwari ",
            "optionC": "  Rae Rekho ",
            "optionD": "  Sardeshmukhi ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t'Sardeshmukhi' is an additional 10% tax levied upon the collected 'Chauth'. The reasons for the additional tax was due to the King claiming hereditary rights upon the tax collection.This revenue assessment is related to the Vijayanagara Empire. ",
            "keyString": "535249s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Shivaji crowned himself at",
            "optionA": "  Poona ",
            "optionB": "  Konkan ",
            "optionC": "  Bijapur ",
            "optionD": "  Raigarh ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tShivaji was crowned king of Maratha Swaraj in a lavish ceremony on 6 June 1674 at Raigarh fort. ",
            "keyString": "535285s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Shivaji maintained a fleet at",
            "optionA": "  Surat ",
            "optionB": "  Calicut ",
            "optionC": "  Bombay ",
            "optionD": "  Kolaba ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tShivaji maintained a fleet at Kolaba to plunder the Mughal trading vessels and also to check the pirates. ",
            "keyString": "535302s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Shivaji submitted to Jai Singh and signed the treaty of",
            "optionA": "  Poona ",
            "optionB": "  Purandhar ",
            "optionC": "  Konkan ",
            "optionD": "  Surat ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Treaty of Purandar was signed on June 11, 1665, between the Rajput ruler Jai Singh I, who was commander of the Mughal Empire, and Maratha Chhatrapati Shivaji Maharaj. Shivaji was forced to sign the agreement after Jai Singh besieged Purandar fort. ",
            "keyString": "535318s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under Shivaji's rule, the head of a unit of 25 in the Cavalry was known as",
            "optionA": "  Jumadar ",
            "optionB": "  Havaldar ",
            "optionC": "  Faujdar ",
            "optionD": "  Hazari ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOne unit in the cavalry was formed of 25 troopers; over them was placed a havaldar, and five havaldars formed one jumla under a jumladar. Ten jumladars made a hazari charge, and five hazaris were placed under a panjhazari, who was given a salary of 2000 huns. ",
            "keyString": "535333s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Brahmin minister of Sambhaji (Son and Successor of Shivaji) upon whom he invested the title of 'Pinnacle of Poets' was",
            "optionA": "  Kavi Kalash ",
            "optionB": "  Kavindra Acharya ",
            "optionC": "  Kavi Bhusan ",
            "optionD": "  Kavi Martanda ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Brahmin minister of Sambhaji (Son and Successor of Shivaji) upon whom he invested the title of 'Pinnacle of Poets' was Kavi Kalash. ",
            "keyString": "594299s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many times Shivaji plundered Surat?",
            "optionA": "  Four Times ",
            "optionB": "  Once ",
            "optionC": "  Thrice ",
            "optionD": "  Twice ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSurat was an important commerical city. Shivaji looted Surat twice in 1664 and 1670. ",
            "keyString": "594335s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Shivaji's administration owed its origin to the principles laid down by",
            "optionA": "  Kautilya ",
            "optionB": "  Sher Shah ",
            "optionC": "  Akbar ",
            "optionD": "  Adi Granth ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tShivaji's administration owed its origin to the principles laid down by Kautilya. ",
            "keyString": "594351s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under Shivaji each province was under a",
            "optionA": "  Viceroy ",
            "optionB": "  Governor ",
            "optionC": "  Diwan ",
            "optionD": "  Zamindar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tShivaji divided his kingdom into four provinces. Each province was under the head called Mamlatdar or Viceroy. Each province was divided into several districts and villages. The village was an organised institution. ",
            "keyString": "594365s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Shivaji Festival was inaugurated in 1895 by",
            "optionA": "  Hume ",
            "optionB": "  Morley ",
            "optionC": "  Tilak ",
            "optionD": "  Gokhale ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTilak initiated Ganeshotsav and Shivaji Utsav in 1894. Soon he came to be regarded as the undisputed leader of Maharashtra and was honored with the title 'Lokamanya' in 1893 which became synonymous with him in the 1900. \"Celebration of Ganapati Festival started this year on 16th September. ",
            "keyString": "594378s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following are true about Shivaji?\nI. He was a disciple of Ramdas Samarth.\nII. He levied Chauth and Sardeshmukhi.\nIII. He became the Peshwa",
            "optionA": "  I, II and III ",
            "optionB": "  II and III ",
            "optionC": "  I and II ",
            "optionD": "  III and I ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tShivaji was a disciple of Ramdas Samarth. Shivaji introduced the collection of two taxes called the Chauth and 'Sardeshmukhi'. ",
            "keyString": "655363s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Marathas first served the rulers of",
            "optionA": "  Muhammadan kingdoms of the south ",
            "optionB": "  Mughal empire ",
            "optionC": "  Vijayanagar ",
            "optionD": "  Afghanistan ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Marathas first served the rulers of Muhammadan kingdoms of the south. ",
            "keyString": "655399s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Maratha Kingdom under the Peshwas was",
            "optionA": "  a loose federation ",
            "optionB": "  a military State ",
            "optionC": "  a confederacy (Mandala or Sangha) ",
            "optionD": "  a regency of the Peshwa ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Maratha Empire or the Maratha Confederacy (Mandala or Sangha) was an Indian power that dominated much of the Indian subcontinent in the 17th and 18th century. The empire formally existed from 1674 with the coronation of Chhatrapati Shivaji and ended in 1818 with the defeat of Peshwa Bajirao II. ",
            "keyString": "655414s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "With the help of Baghnuk (Tiger-claws) Shivaji killed",
            "optionA": "  Afzal khan ",
            "optionB": "  Shayista khan ",
            "optionC": "  Muhamad Khan ",
            "optionD": "  Aurangzeb ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKilling of Afzal Khan is one of the important milestones in Shivaji's life. He carried a weapon called wagh nakh (\"tiger claws\"), consisting of an iron finger-grip to attack Afzal Khan. ",
            "keyString": "655427s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Maratha dominion of Shivaji was known as",
            "optionA": "  Swaraj ",
            "optionB": "  Mulk-i-qadim ",
            "optionC": "  Maharajya ",
            "optionD": "  Maratha Rastra ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tShivaji (1627-1680) was a Maratha aristocrat of the Bhosle clan who is considered to be the founder of the Maratha empire. Shivaji led a resistance to free the Marathi people from the Sultanate of Bijapur from 1645 and establish Hindavi Swarajya (self-rule of Hindu people). ",
            "keyString": "655439s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Chhatrapati Sambhaji (1680-1688 AD) was the ruler of which dynasty?",
            "optionA": "  Maratha ",
            "optionB": "  Nanda ",
            "optionC": "  Haryanka ",
            "optionD": "  Maurya ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChhatrapati Sambhaji was the Maratha ruler (1680-1688 AD). He was the eldest son of Chhatrapati Shivaji Maharaj and Maharani Saibai. ",
            "keyString": "712274s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bajirao-I (1720-1740 AD) was the ruler of which dynasty?",
            "optionA": "  Nanda ",
            "optionB": "  Peshwas ",
            "optionC": "  Haryanka ",
            "optionD": "  Maurya ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBaji Rao (18 August 1700 \u2013 28 April 1740) was a general of the Maratha Empire in India. He served as Peshwa (General) to the fifth Maratha Chhatrapati (Emperor) Shahu from 1720 until his death. He is also known by the name Bajirao Ballal. ",
            "keyString": "712310s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Chhatrapati Shivaji Maharaj (1674-1680 AD) was the ruler of which dynasty?",
            "optionA": "  Nanda ",
            "optionB": "  Haryanka ",
            "optionC": "  Maurya ",
            "optionD": "  Maratha ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChatrapati Shivaji Maharaj (1630\u20131680) was a Maratha aristocrat of the Bhosale clan who is considered to be the founder of the Maratha empire. ",
            "keyString": "712326s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Baji Rao-II (1796-1818 A.D.) was the ruler of which dynasty?",
            "optionA": "  Nanda ",
            "optionB": "  Haryanka ",
            "optionC": "  Maurya ",
            "optionD": "  Peshwas ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBaji Rao II (10 January, 1775 \u2013 28 January, 1851) was the last Peshwa of the Maratha Empire, and governed from 1795 to 1818. He was installed as a puppet ruler by the Maratha nobles, whose growing power prompted him to flee his capital Pune and sign the Treaty of Bassein (1802) with the British. ",
            "keyString": "712340s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Identify the European power from whom Shivaji obtained cannons and ammunition",
            "optionA": "  The French ",
            "optionB": "  The Portuguese ",
            "optionC": "  The Dutch ",
            "optionD": "  The English ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHe used cannons and ammunition from the Portuguese to attack the English. In June 1661, Shivaji's soldiers plundered Rajapur and captured several Englishmen. This was payback for the english aid to Bijapur. The folowing year he captured a band of Englishmen in Surat for supplying ammunition to his enemies. ",
            "keyString": "712352s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following was NOT introduced by Shivaji?",
            "optionA": "  Land-tax ",
            "optionB": "  Chauth ",
            "optionC": "  Sardeshmukhi ",
            "optionD": "  Pilgrim tax ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPilgrim tax was not introduced by Shivaji. ",
            "keyString": "756614s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mzal Khan who fought with Shivaji was the ruler of",
            "optionA": "  Bijapur ",
            "optionB": "  Mewar ",
            "optionC": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionD": "  Bengal ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMzal Khan who fought with Shivaji was the ruler of Bijapur. ",
            "keyString": "756649s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In his early days Shivaji moved with",
            "optionA": "  Jat leaders ",
            "optionB": "  Mawali leaders ",
            "optionC": "  Santhals ",
            "optionD": "  Bhils ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn his early days Shivaji moved with Mawali leaders. ",
            "keyString": "816960s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Shivaji crowned himself as King in the year",
            "optionA": "  1664 ",
            "optionB": "  1674 ",
            "optionC": "  1670 ",
            "optionD": "  1660 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tShivaji was crowned on this day in 1674. The founder of the Maratha empire was formally crowned as Chhatrapati of Raigad on this day, June 6, in the year 1674. ",
            "keyString": "817056s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "After the death of Rajaram in 1700A.D., Marathas continued the war against the Mughals under his brave wife",
            "optionA": "  Tarabai ",
            "optionB": "  Lakshmibai ",
            "optionC": "  Ramabi ",
            "optionD": "  Jijabai ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t After the death of Rajaram (1700 A.D) Marathas continued the war against the Mughals under the leadership of Tarabai (Garurdion of Shivaji-II). When Bajirao came to power, the mughal empire was much weakened. The credit to the weakening of the mughals goes not to Bajirao but to his predecessors like Shivaji, Shivaji's son Sambhaji, Shivaji's second son Rajaram and later Rajaram's wife Tarabai also to generals like Santaji and Dhanaji who fought for Rajaram. ",
            "keyString": "817091s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sambaji plundered the Mughal territories in",
            "optionA": "  Deccan ",
            "optionB": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionC": "  Punjab ",
            "optionD": "  Bengal ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1664 and 1670, Shivaji had organized two plundering raids on Surat, which was a part of Mughal territory. The rulers of Deccan were already familiar with these terms well before Shivaji. In fact, Portuguese had also paid these taxes to the neighbouring kings of their territories to avoid conflicts with them. ",
            "keyString": "817121s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The estate of Shivaji's father was",
            "optionA": "  Konkan ",
            "optionB": "  Poona ",
            "optionC": "  Torna ",
            "optionD": "  Rajgarh ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tShivaji was born in the hill-fort of Shivneri, near the city of Junnar in what is now Pune district. Scholars disagree on his date of birth. Shivaji was named after a local deity, the goddess Shivai. Shivaji's father Shahaji Bhonsle was a Maratha general who served the Deccan Sultanates. ",
            "keyString": "817146s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Shivaji ceded the forts to the Mughals by the treaty of",
            "optionA": "  Chittor ",
            "optionB": "  Pune ",
            "optionC": "  Purandar ",
            "optionD": "  Torna ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTreaty of Purander (1665) was signed between the Maratha Emperor Chhatrapati Shivaji Maharaj and the Mughal military commander - Rajput Raja Jai Singh (on behalf of Emperor Aurangzeb) According to this Treaty: Shivaji ceded his forts to the Mughal and promised to provide imperial service of 5000 soldiers.",
            "keyString": "869026s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Administrative Council of Shivaji was known as",
            "optionA": "  Parishad ",
            "optionB": "  Mantriparishad ",
            "optionC": "  Ashtapradhan ",
            "optionD": "  Rajyaparishad ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Ashta Pradhan (also termed Asta Pradhad or the Council of 8) was a council of eight ministers that administered the Maratha empire. The council was formed in 1674 by their king, Chatrapati Shivaji Maharaj. ",
            "keyString": "870021s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under the administration of Shivaji, \"Peshwa\" was referred to as",
            "optionA": "  Minister of Religious Affairs ",
            "optionB": "  Minister of Defence ",
            "optionC": "  Chief Minister ",
            "optionD": "  Minister of Justice ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPeshwa, the office of chief minister among the Maratha people of India. The peshwa, also known as the mukhya pradhan, originally headed the advisory council of the raja Shivaji (reigned c. 1659\u201380). ",
            "keyString": "870116s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Assertion (A): Shivaji aimed at establishing Maratha rule in Delhi. \nReason (R): Shivaji took the leadership of the Maratha resistance against the Mughals.",
            "optionA": "  Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A ",
            "optionB": "  Both A and R are true but R is not a correct explanation of A ",
            "optionC": "  A is true but R is false ",
            "optionD": "  A is false but R is true ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThis was an era when the Mughals and the Marathas were constantly at war for control over the Deccan. In 1674, Shivaji had been crowned the ruler of the independent Maratha kingdom established by him. Under his able leadership, the empire quickly became a key political force in India at the height of Mughal power. ",
            "keyString": "870158s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The guerilla warfare was pioneered by",
            "optionA": "  Aurangzeb ",
            "optionB": "  Akbar ",
            "optionC": "  Shivaji ",
            "optionD": "  Balaji Rao ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChhatrapati Shivaji Maharaj started guerrilla warfare against the Mughals and other powers in 1645 leading to the establishment of the Maratha state in 1674, sowing seeds of what would become the last great empire (Maratha empire) in free India. ",
            "keyString": "870182s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Shivaji's Agra Adventure was planned by",
            "optionA": "  Afzal Khan ",
            "optionB": "  Shayista Khan ",
            "optionC": "  Jai Singh ",
            "optionD": "  Mir Jumla ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJai Singh advised Shivaji to proceed to Agra and meet the Mughal emperor Aurangzeb to ratify the treaty. Jai Singh assured Shivaji that he would not be harmed during his journey to and stay at Agra. Shivaji saw the truce as an opportunity for respite and to consolidate his strength. ",
            "keyString": "943958s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Name the religious personality who exercised a great influence over Shivaji",
            "optionA": "  Tukaram ",
            "optionB": "  Guru Nanak Dev ",
            "optionC": "  Mirabai ",
            "optionD": "  Guru Ram Das ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGuru Ram Das was a spiritual guru of Shivaji. Shivaji gave a Sanad to the fort of Parli to Ramdas. The fort was later renamed Sajjangad. Ramdas not only spiritually, but also advised Shivaji on tactical and warfare strategies. ",
            "keyString": "944085s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Shivaji sacked __________ and secured a large booty",
            "optionA": "  Bijapur ",
            "optionB": "  Poona ",
            "optionC": "  Konkan ",
            "optionD": "  Surat ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn January 1664, with 4000 picked Maratha soldiers Sivaji attacked and sacked Surat. He set fire to thousands of houses in Surat. Sivaji left Surat carrying away gold, silver, pearls, and diamonds amounting to more than a crore of rupees. ",
            "keyString": "944144s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Peshwa's Secretariat at Pune (Poona), the pivot of the Maratha government was known as",
            "optionA": "  Huzur Daftar ",
            "optionB": "  El Beriz Daftar ",
            "optionC": "  Chalte Dafter ",
            "optionD": "  Peshwa Dafter ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPeshwa\u2019s office at Poona called Huzur Daftar was the center of Maratha administration. It was an extensive establishment having several offices and different bureaucratic departments. The most important department was the El Beriz Daftar and the Chalte Daftar.",
            "keyString": "944188s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which year, Shivaji was crowned as the Chhatrapati?",
            "optionA": "  1608 ",
            "optionB": "  1674 ",
            "optionC": "  1646 ",
            "optionD": "  1710 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAn Indian warrior king and a member of the Bhonsle Maratha clan, Shivaji was formally crowned as the Chhatrapati (Monarch) of his realm at Raigad in 1674. ",
            "keyString": "944239s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Chhatrapati Shivaji Terminus station was designed by",
            "optionA": "  Frederick William Stevens ",
            "optionB": "  Santiago Calatrava ",
            "optionC": "  Fazlur Rahman Khan ",
            "optionD": "  Frei Otto ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFrederick William Stevens (11 November 1847 \u2013 3 March 1900) was an English architectural engineer who worked for the British colonial government in India. Stevens' most notable design was the railway station Victoria Terminus in Bombay (in 1996 renamed the Chhatrapati Shivaji Terminus in Mumbai). ",
            "keyString": "988589s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Shivaji attacked Shaista Khan in the night at",
            "optionA": "  Agra ",
            "optionB": "  Konkan ",
            "optionC": "  Bijapur ",
            "optionD": "  Poona ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt is one of the most famous exploits of Shivaji early in his career and has never been forgotten by successive generations in India. Shaista Khan, the maternal uncle of Emperor Aurangzeb, and the new Governor of Deccan, had made Shivaji's position precarious by his furious offensive. He had even occupied Pune (9th May 1660). Shivaji had already lost Chakan (August 1660), Kalian (May 1661), and in March 1663 the Maratha commander Netaji Palker was worsted in a sanguary fight and he had to escape losing much of the booty being brought from the Mughal territory. ",
            "keyString": "988632s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Shivaji started his public career at the age of",
            "optionA": "  18 ",
            "optionB": "  21 ",
            "optionC": "  23 ",
            "optionD": "  24 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tShivaji showed his mettle at the young age of 18, when he overran a number of hill forts near Poona - Rajgarh, Kondana and Torana during 1645-1647. ",
            "keyString": "988655s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The most powerful Peshwa was",
            "optionA": "  Balaji Baji Rao ",
            "optionB": "  Baji Rao-I ",
            "optionC": "  Madhava Rao ",
            "optionD": "  Balaji Vishwanath ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBaji Rao-I (The Son of Bala ji Vishwanath) was the most powerful Peshwa. He is also known as the winner 72 wars and Baji Rao Mastani.",
            "keyString": "988683s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Tarabai, who conducted the affairs of the Maratha government from 1700 to 1707 AD, was the widow of the Maratha King",
            "optionA": "  Shambhaji ",
            "optionB": "  Shivaji II ",
            "optionC": "  Raja Ram ",
            "optionD": "  Shivaji III ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTarabai Bhosale (14 April 1675 \u2013 9 December 1761) was the regent of the Maratha Empire of India from 1700 until 1708. She was the queen of Chhatrapati Rajaram Bhosale, daughter-in-law of the empire's founder Shivaji and mother of Shivaji II. ",
            "keyString": "988702s9m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During Shivaji's rule the Council of the State consisted of",
            "optionA": "  Eight Ministers ",
            "optionB": "  Eighteen Ministers ",
            "optionC": "  Twelve Ministers ",
            "optionD": "  Fifteen Ministers ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Ashta Pradhan (also termed Asta Pradhad or the Council of 8) was a council of eight ministers that administered the Maratha empire. The council was formed in 1674 by their king, Chatrapati Shivaji Maharaj. ",
            "keyString": "40877s10m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following was the capital of Shivaji?",
            "optionA": "  Poona ",
            "optionB": "  Raigarh ",
            "optionC": "  Singhgarh ",
            "optionD": "  Panhala ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMaratha ruler Chhatrapati Shvaji created independent Maratha Kingdom with Raigarh (Maharashtra) is his Capital. Raigad was the capital of the Marathas under Chhatrapati Shivaji Maharaj. ",
            "keyString": "41026s10m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "After his coronation Shivaji assumed the title of",
            "optionA": "  Maharaja ",
            "optionB": "  Peshwa ",
            "optionC": "  Chhatrapati ",
            "optionD": "  Samrat ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfter his coronation Shivaji assumed the title of Chhatrapati Maharaja. ",
            "keyString": "41099s10m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "On behalf of Aurangzeb Shivaji attacked",
            "optionA": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionB": "  Konkan ",
            "optionC": "  Surat ",
            "optionD": "  Poena ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring Aurangzeb's march against Bijapur, Shivaji offered his services to him and began to attack the Konkan on behalf of the Mughals. Aurangzeb was called away by the war of succession in the north. Shivaji occupied almost whole of the Konkan. ",
            "keyString": "41170s10m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The liberal religion preached by the saints of Maharashtra and rigidly followed by Shivaji is known as",
            "optionA": "  Desh Dharma ",
            "optionB": "  Maharashtra Dharma ",
            "optionC": "  Rashtra Dharma ",
            "optionD": "  Hindu Dharma ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe liberal religion preached by the saints of Maharashtra and rigidly followed by Shivaji is known as Maharashtra Dharma. ",
            "keyString": "41227s10m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Shivaji founded the Maratha kingdom by annexing the territories of",
            "optionA": "  Bijapur ",
            "optionB": "  Mughals ",
            "optionC": "  Both (a) and (b) above ",
            "optionD": "  Bijapur, Golcunda and the Mughals ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfter a lifetime of warfare with Adilshah of Bijapur and Mughal emperor Aurangzeb, Shivaji founded an independent Maratha kingdom in 1674 with Raigad as its capital. ",
            "keyString": "84254s10m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the capital of Shivaji's Kingdom?",
            "optionA": "  Pune ",
            "optionB": "  Raigarh ",
            "optionC": "  Karwar ",
            "optionD": "  Purandhar ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tShivaji founded an independent Hindu Maratha Kingdom in 1674 with Raigarh as its capital. ",
            "keyString": "84289s10m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "'Chauth' was",
            "optionA": "  A religious tax imposed by Aurangzeb ",
            "optionB": "  Toll tax imposed by Shivaji ",
            "optionC": "  Irrigation tax charged by Akbar ",
            "optionD": "  Land tax levied by Shivaji on neighbouring\nStates ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChauth (from Sanskrit meaning one-fourth) was a regular tax or tribute imposed, from early 18th century, by the Maratha Empire in India. It was an annual tax nominally levied at 25% on revenue or produce, hence the name. It was levied on the lands which were under nominal Mughal rule. It is a tribute paid to the king. ",
            "keyString": "84306s10m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The second founder of the Maratha Kingdom was",
            "optionA": "  Tarabai ",
            "optionB": "  Peshwa Balaji Vishwanath ",
            "optionC": "  Peshwa Bajirao ",
            "optionD": "  Shahu ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBalaji Vishwanath assisted a young Maratha Emperor Shahu to consolidate his grip on a kingdom that had been racked by civil war and persistent attack by the Mughals under Aurangzeb. He was called \"the second founder of the Maratha State.\" ",
            "keyString": "84320s10m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Mughal General, who decisively defeated Shivaji and forced him to conclude the Treaty of Purandar, was",
            "optionA": "  Shaista Khan ",
            "optionB": "  Mirza Raja Jai Singh ",
            "optionC": "  Prince Muazzam ",
            "optionD": "  Dilir Khan ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tShivaji was forced to sign the agreement after Jai Singh besieged Purandar fort. When Shivaji realised that war with the Mughal Empire would only cause damage to the empire and that his men would suffer heavy losses, he chose to make a treaty instead of leaving his men under the Mughals. ",
            "keyString": "84334s10m44h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        }
    ]
}